[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
TOM CRUISE: I'm going to show you some magic.
汤姆·克鲁斯：我要展示一些魔法。
It's the real thing.
这是真的。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
I mean, it's all the real thing.
我的意思是，这一切都是真的。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
大卫·马兰：好的。
This is CS50, Harvard University's Introduction
这是CS50，哈佛大学的导论
to the Intellectual Enterprises of Computer Science
到计算机科学的智力事业
and the Art of Programming.
和编程艺术。
My name is David Malan, and this is our family-friendly introduction
我的名字是大卫·马兰，这是我们适合家庭观看的导论
to artificial intelligence or AI, which seems to be everywhere these days.
到人工智能，或者说AI，这些天它似乎无处不在。
But first, a word on these rubber ducks, which your students
但首先，关于这些橡皮鸭，你的学生
might have had for some time.
可能已经拥有一段时间了。
Within the world of computer science, and programming in particular,
在计算机科学领域，尤其是编程，
there's this notion of rubber duck debugging or rubber ducking--
有一种说法叫做橡皮鸭调试或橡皮鸭法——
--whereby in the absence of a colleague, a friend, a family member, a teaching
——即在没有同事、朋友、家人、老师的情况下，
fellow who might be able to answer your questions about your code,
可能会回答你关于代码的问题，
especially when it's not working, ideally you
尤其是在代码无法工作时，理想情况下你
might have at least a rubber duck or really any inanimate
至少应该有一只橡皮鸭，或者任何无生命的
object on your desk with whom to talk.
物体放在你的桌子上，用来和它说话。
And the idea is, that in expressing your logic, talking through your problems,
它的想法是，在表达你的逻辑，把你的问题讲出来，
even though the duck doesn't actually respond,
即使鸭子没有真正回应，
invariably, you hear eventually the illogic in your thoughts
不可避免地，你最终会听到你的想法中的逻辑错误
and the proverbial light bulb goes off.
然后那颗象征性的灯泡就亮了。
Now, for students online for some time, CS50
现在，对于在线学习了一段时间的学生来说，CS50
has had a digital version thereof, whereby
已经有了它的数字版本，也就是
in the programming environment that CS50 students use,
在CS50学生使用的编程环境中，
for the past several years, if they don't have a rubber duck on their desk,
在过去几年里，如果他们没有在桌子上放一只橡皮鸭，
they can pull up this interface here.
他们就可以打开这里这个界面。
And if they begin a conversation like, I'm
如果他们开始一段对话，比如，我
hoping you can help me solve some problem, up until recently,
希望你能帮我解决一些问题，直到最近，
CS50's virtual rubber duck would simply quack once, twice,
CS50的虚拟橡皮鸭只会呱呱叫一次，两次，
or three times in total.
或者总共三次。
But we have anecdotal evidence that alone
但我们有轶事证据表明，仅仅
was enough to get students to realize what it is they were doing wrong.
就已经足以让学生意识到他们做错了什么。
But of course, more recently has this duck and so many other ducks,
但当然，最近这只鸭子，以及世界上许多其他的鸭子，
so to speak, around the world, come to life really.
可以这么说，全世界都真的活了过来。
And your students have been using artificial intelligence
而你的学生一直在使用人工智能
in some form within CS50 as a virtual teaching assistant.
在CS50中以虚拟助教的形式出现。
And what we'll do today, is reveal not only
而我们今天要做的是，不仅揭示
how we've been using and leveraging AI within CS50,
我们如何在CS50中使用和利用AI，
but also how AI itself works, and to prepare you better for the years ahead.
还有AI本身是如何运作的，以及如何更好地为未来几年做准备。
So last year around this time, like DALL-E 2 and image generation
所以去年这个时候，就像DALL-E 2和图像生成
were all of the rage.
都很火爆。
You might have played with this, whereby you can type in some keywords and boom,
你可能玩过这个，你可以输入一些关键词，然后砰的一声，
you have a dynamically generated image.
你就有了动态生成的图片。
Similar tools are like Midjourney, which gives you even more realistic 3D
类似的工具还有Midjourney，它能给你更逼真的3D
imagery.
图像。
And within that world of image generation,
在图像生成的世界里，
there were nonetheless some tells, like an observant viewer could tell
尽管如此，还是有一些迹象，比如一个观察敏锐的观众可以分辨出
that this was probably generated by AI.
这很有可能是AI生成的。
And in fact, a few months ago, The New York Times
事实上，几个月前，《纽约时报》
took a look at some of these tools.
对这些工具中的一些进行了研究。
And so, for instance, here is a sequence of images
因此，例如，这里有一系列图像
that at least at left, isn't all that implausible that this
至少在左边，这并不完全不可能是
might be an actual photograph.
一张真实的图片。
But in fact, all three of these are AI-generated.
但事实上，这三张图片都是AI生成的。
And for some time, there was a certain tell.
在一段时间内，存在一个明显的迹象。
Like AI up until recently, really wasn't really good at the finer details,
就好像AI直到最近，在处理更精细的细节方面，做得并不好，
like the fingers are not quite right.
比如手指就不太对。
And so you could have that sort of hint.
所以你可以得到这种提示。
But I dare say, AI is getting even better and better,
但我要说，AI正在变得越来越好，
such that it's getting harder to discern these kinds of things.
因此，要辨别出这些东西越来越难了。
So if you haven't already, go ahead and take out your phone
所以，如果你还没有，那就拿出你的手机
if you have one with you.
如果你有的话。
And if you'd like to partake, scan this barcode here,
如果你想参与，就扫描一下这里的二维码，
which will lead you to a URL.
它会带你到一个网址。
And on your screen, you'll have an opportunity in a moment to buzz in.
在你的屏幕上，你将有机会在片刻后进入。
If my colleague, Rongxin, wouldn't mind joining me up here on stage.
如果我的同事荣欣不介意和我一起上台。
We'll ask you a sequence of questions and see just how
我们会问你一系列问题，看看你到底
prepared you are for this coming world of AI.
为即将到来的AI世界做好了多少准备。
So for instance, once you've got this here,
所以，比如，一旦你有了这个，
code scanned, if you don't, that's fine.
代码扫描，如果你没有，那就没关系。
You can play along at home or alongside the person next to you.
你可以在家玩，或者和你旁边的人一起玩。
Here are two images.
这里有两张图片。
And my question for you is, which of these two images, left
我要问你的问题是，这两张图片中，哪一张是AI生成的，左边
or right, was generated by AI?
还是右边？
Which of these two was generated by AI, left or right?
这两张图片中，哪一张是AI生成的，左边还是右边？
And I think Rongxin, we can flip over and see
我想荣欣，我们可以翻过来看看
as the responses start to come in.
随着回应开始进来。
So far, we're about 20% saying left, 70 plus percent saying right.
到目前为止，大约20%的人说左边，70%以上的人说右边。
3%, 4%, comfortably admitting unsure, and that's fine.
3%、4%，坦然承认不确定，这很好。
Let's wait for a few more responses to come in,
让我们等一下再收到一些回复，
though I think the right-hand folks have it.
不过我认为右边的人是对的。
And let's go ahead and flip back and see what the solution is.
让我们翻回去看看答案是什么。
In this case, it was, in fact, the right-hand side that was AI-generated.
在这种情况下，实际上，是右边的图像是由AI生成的。
So, that's great.
所以，太好了。
I'm not sure what it means that we figured this one out,
我不知道我们解出这道题意味着什么，
but let's try one more here.
但让我们再试一下。
So let me propose that we consider now these two images.
所以，我建议我们现在看看这两张图片。
It's the same code.
代码是相同的。
So if you still have your phone up, you don't need to scan again.
所以如果你还拿着你的手机，你不需要再扫描。
It's going to be the same URL here.
网址还是一样的。
But just in case you closed it.
但以防万一你关掉了。
Let's take a look now at these two images.
现在让我们看看这两张图片。
Which of these, left or right, was AI-generated?
这两张图片中，哪一张是AI生成的，左边还是右边？
Left or right this time?
这次是左还是右？
Rongxin, should we take a look at how it's coming in?
荣欣，我们来看看结果如何？
Oh, it's a little closer this time.
哦，这次更接近了。
Left or right?
左还是右？
Right's losing a little ground, maybe as people
右边的票数正在略微下降，也许是因为人们
are changing their answers to left.
正在把答案改成左边。
More people are unsure this time, which is somewhat revealing.
这次更多人表示不确定，这多少有点意味深长。
Let's give folks another second or two.
我们再给人们一两秒钟的时间。
And Rongxin, should we flip back?
荣欣，我们翻回去看看吗？
The answer is, actually a trick question, since they were both AI.
其实，这是一个诡计，因为它们都是 AI。
So most of you, most of you were, in fact, right.
所以你们大多数人，事实上是正确的。
But if you take a glance at this, is getting really, really good.
但如果你看看这个，它真的非常非常棒。
And so this is just a taste of the images that we might see down the line.
所以，这只是我们将来可能看到的图像的一个缩影。
And in fact, that video with which we began,
事实上，我们开始播放的视频，
Tom Cruise, as you might have gleaned, was not, in fact, Tom Cruise.
汤姆·克鲁斯，正如你可能已经猜到，实际上并不是汤姆·克鲁斯。
That was an example of a deepfake, a video that
那是深度伪造的一个例子，一个视频
was synthesized, whereby a different human was acting out those motions,
是合成的，其中一个不同的人在模仿那些动作，
saying those words, but software, artificial intelligence-inspired
说着那些话，但软件，人工智能启发的
software was mutating the actual image and faking this video.
软件正在改变真实图像，并伪造这个视频。
So it's all fun and games for now as we tinker with these kinds of examples,
所以现在我们用这些例子来玩玩，这都是很有趣的游戏，
but suffice it to say, as we've begun to discuss in classes like this already,
但可以肯定地说，正如我们已经在这样的课堂上开始讨论的那样，
disinformation is only going to become more challenging in a world where
在这样一个文字不再是唯一传播方式的世界里，虚假信息只会变得更具挑战性，
it's not just text, but it's imagery.
因为不只是文字，还有图像。
And all the more, soon video.
而且很快，还会出现视频。
But for today, we'll focus really on the fundamentals, what
但今天，我们将重点关注基础知识，了解
it is that's enabling technologies like these, and even more familiarly, text
是什么让像这样的技术成为可能，更熟悉的是，文本
generation, which is all the rage.
生成，这可是当今的潮流。
And in fact, it seems just a few months ago, probably everyone in this room
事实上，就在几个月前，这个房间里的每个人
started to hear about tools like ChatGPT.
都开始听说 ChatGPT 之类的工具。
So we thought we'd do one final exercise here as a group.
所以我们想在这里做一个最后的练习，作为一组。
And this was another piece in The New York Times
而这是《纽约时报》的另一篇文章
where they asked the audience, "Did a fourth grader write this?
他们问观众：“这是四年级学生写的吗？
Or the new chatbot?"
还是新的聊天机器人？”
So another opportunity to assess your discerning skills.
所以，这是评估你判断力的好机会。
So same URL.
所以，相同的 URL。
So if you still have your phone open and that same interface open,
所以，如果你仍然打开手机和相同的界面，
you're in the right place.
你就来对了地方。
And here, we'll take a final stab at two essays of sorts.
在这里，我们将对两种类型的文章进行最后的尝试。
Which of these essays was written by AI?
这两篇文章中哪一篇是 AI 写的？
Essay 1 or Essay 2?
是文章 1 还是文章 2？
And as folks buzz in, I'll read the first.
当人们开始回答时，我会读第一篇。
Essay 1.
文章 1。
I like to bring a yummy sandwich and a cold juice box for lunch.
我喜欢带一个美味的三明治和一盒冷果汁去吃午饭。
Sometimes I'll even pack a tasty piece of fruit or a bag of crunchy chips.
有时，我甚至会带一块美味的水果或一袋脆薯条。
As we eat, we chat and laugh and catch up on each other's day, dot, dot, dot.
我们边吃边聊天，边笑，边聊彼此的一天，等等。
Essay 2.
文章 2。
My mother packs me a sandwich, a drink, fruit, and a treat.
我的妈妈给我打包了三明治、饮料、水果和零食。
When I get in the lunchroom, I find an empty table and sit there
当我走进餐厅时，我找到一张空桌子，然后坐在那里
and I eat my lunch.
然后我吃午饭。
My friends come and sit down with me.
我的朋友们来和我坐在一起。
Dot, dot, dot.
等等。
Rongxin, should we see what folks think?
荣欣，我们来看看大家怎么想？
It looks like most of you think that Essay 1 was generated by AI.
看起来你们大多数人认为文章 1 是 AI 生成的。
And in fact, if we flip back to the answer here, it was, in fact, Essay 1.
事实上，如果我们翻回到答案，文章 1 确实是 AI 生成的。
So it's great that we now already have seemingly this discerning eye,
所以，我们现在似乎已经有了这样的辨别能力，这真是太好了，
but let me perhaps deflate that enthusiasm
但也许让我浇灭一下你们的热情
by saying it's only going to get harder to discern one from the other.
因为区分它们只会变得越来越难。
And we're really now on the bleeding edge of what's soon to be possible.
我们现在正处于即将成为现实的技术前沿。
But most everyone in this room has probably by now
但这个房间里的每个人现在可能都
seen, tried, certainly heard of ChatGPT, which is all about textual generation.
看到过、尝试过、当然也听说过 ChatGPT，它就是关于文本生成的。
Within CS50 and within academia more generally,
在 CS50 和整个学术界，
have we been thinking about, talking about, how whether to use or not
我们一直在思考、讨论，如何使用或不使用
use these kinds of technologies.
这些技术。
And if the students in the room haven't told the family members in the room
如果房间里的学生还没有告诉房间里的家人
already, this here is an excerpt from CS50's own syllabus this year,
那么，这里摘录了今年 CS50 的教学大纲，
whereby we have deemed tools like ChatGPT in their current form,
我们认为像 ChatGPT 这样的工具，以目前的形态，
just too helpful.
太有用。
Sort of like an overzealous friend who in school,
就像一个在学校里过分热心的朋友，
who just wants to give you all of the answers instead of leading you to them.
他只想给你所有的答案，而不是引导你找到答案。
And so we simply prohibit by policy using AI-based software,
所以，我们简单地禁止使用基于 AI 的软件，
such as ChatGPT, third-party tools like GitHub Copilot, Bing Chat, and others
比如 ChatGPT、GitHub Copilot、Bing Chat 和其他类似的第三方工具
that suggests or completes answers to questions or lines of code.
它们会建议或完成问题的答案或代码行。
But it would seem reactionary to take away what technology surely has
但是，剥夺技术可能具有的某些潜在优势似乎是倒退的。
some potential upsides for education.
对于教育来说，有些潜在的优势。
And so within CS50 this semester, as well as this past summer,
所以，在本学期，以及去年夏天，在 CS50 中，
have we allowed students to use CS50's own AI-based software, which
我们允许学生使用 CS50 自己开发的 AI 软件，这些软件
are in effect, as we'll discuss, built on top
实际上，正如我们即将讨论的那样，它们建立在
of these third-party tools, ChatGPT from OpenAI,
这些第三方工具的基础之上，比如 OpenAI 的 ChatGPT，
companies like Microsoft and beyond.
以及微软等公司。
And in fact, what students can now use, is this brought to life CS50 duck,
事实上，学生现在可以使用的是，这诞生了 CS50 鸭子，
or DDB, Duck Debugger, within a website of our own,
或者说 DDB，鸭子调试器，在我们自己的网站上，
CS50 AI, and another that your students know known as cs50.dev.
CS50 AI，以及另一个你的学生们都知道的网站 cs50.dev。
So students are using it, but in a way where
所以，学生们正在使用它，但使用的方式是
we have tempered the enthusiasm of what might otherwise
我们已经抑制了可能出现的过度热情的想法，
be an overly helpful duck to model it more
把这只鸭子塑造成更像
akin to a good teacher, a good teaching fellow,
一位好老师，一位好的助教，
who might guide you to the answers, but not simply hand them outright.
他们可能会引导你找到答案，但不会直接把答案给你。
So what does that actually mean, and in what form does this duck come?
那么，这究竟意味着什么，这只鸭子以什么形式存在呢？
Well, architecturally, for those of you with engineering backgrounds that
从架构上来说，对于那些有工程背景的人来说，
might be curious as to how this is actually implemented,
可能会好奇这究竟是如何实现的，
if a student here in the class has a question, virtually in this case,
如果班上的某个学生有疑问，在本例中，是虚拟的，
they somehow ask these questions of this central web application, cs50.ai.
他们以某种方式向这个名为cs50.ai的中心网络应用程序提出这些问题。
But we, in turn, have built much of our own logic
但我们反过来构建了很多我们自己的逻辑
on top of third-party services, known as APIs, application programming
建立在第三方服务的基础上，被称为API，应用程序编程
interfaces, features that other companies provide
接口，其他公司提供的功能
that people like us can use.
我们可以使用。
So as they are doing really a lot of the heavy lifting,
所以，由于他们正在做很多繁重的工作，
the so-called large language models are there.
这些所谓的“大型语言模型”就出现了。
But we, too, have information that is not in these models yet.
但我们也拥有这些模型中尚未包含的信息。
For instance, the words that came out of my mouth
例如，我上周讲课时说的话，
just last week when we had a lecture on some other topic, not to mention all
上周我们讲了其他主题的课程时，更不用说所有
of the past lectures and homework assignments from this year.
过去的讲座和今年的作业。
So we have our own vector database locally
因此，我们在本地拥有自己的向量数据库
via which we can search for more recent information,
通过它，我们可以搜索更新的信息，
and then hand some of that information into these models, which you might
然后将一些信息输入这些模型，你可能
recall, at least for OpenAI, is cut off as of 2021 as
记得，至少对于OpenAI来说，截至2021年，
of now, to make the information even more current.
为了使信息更加及时。
So architecturally, that's sort of the flow.
所以，从架构上讲，这就是流程。
But for now, I thought I'd share at a higher level what
但现在，我想更深入地分享一下，
it is your students are already familiar with,
你们的学生已经熟悉的，
and what will soon be more broadly available to our own students
以及很快将更广泛地提供给我们自己的学生
online as well.
在线使用。
So what we focused on is, what's generally
所以，我们关注的是，一般来说
now known as prompt engineering, which isn't really a technical phrase,
现在被称为“提示工程”，这不是一个真正的技术术语，
because it's not so much engineering in the traditional sense.
因为它不是传统意义上的工程学。
It really is just English, what we are largely
它实际上就是英语，我们主要
doing when it comes to giving the AI the personality
所做的，就是给AI赋予个性，
of a good teacher or a good duck.
使其像一个好老师或一只好鸭子。
So what we're doing, is giving it what's known as a system prompt nowadays,
所以，我们所做的，就是给它一个现在被称为“系统提示”的东西，
whereby we write some English sentences, send those English sentences to OpenAI
我们写一些英语句子，将这些句子发送到OpenAI
or Microsoft, that sort of teaches it how to behave.
或微软，教会它如何表现。
Not just using its own knowledge out of the box,
不仅仅是使用它自己的知识，
but coercing it to behave a little more educationally constructively.
而是迫使它在教育上更加建设性地表现。
And so for instance, a representative snippet
所以，例如，我们提供给这些服务的代表性片段
of English that we provide to these services
英语看起来像这样。
looks a little something like this.
看起来像这样。
Quote, unquote, "You are a friendly and supportive teaching assistant for CS50.
引号，引号，“你是一个友好且支持性的CS50助教。
You are also a rubber duck.
你也是一只橡胶鸭子。
You answer student questions only about CS50 and the field of computer science,
你只回答与CS50和计算机科学领域相关的学生问题，
do not answer questions about unrelated topics.
不要回答与这些主题无关的问题。
Do not provide full answers to problem sets,
不要提供完整的问题集答案，
as this would violate academic honesty.
因为这会违反学术诚信。
And so in essence, and you can do this manually with ChatGPT,
因此，本质上，你可以手动使用ChatGPT，
you can tell it or ask it how to behave.
你可以告诉它或询问它如何表现。
We, essentially, are doing this automatically,
我们，本质上，是在自动执行这个过程，
so that it doesn't just hand answers out of the box
这样它就不会直接给出答案，
and knows a little something more about us.
而且它会对我们有所了解。
There's also in this world of AI right now the notion of a user
在当今的AI领域，还有一个概念叫做用户
prompt versus that system prompt.
提示与系统提示。
And the user prompt, in our case, is essentially the student's own question.
而用户提示，在我们的情况下，本质上是学生自己的问题。
I have a question about x, or I have a problem with my code here in y,
我有一个关于x的问题，或者我的代码在y中遇到了问题，
so we pass to those same APIs, students' own questions
因此，我们向这些相同的API传递学生自己的问题，
as part of this so-called user prompt.
作为这个所谓的用户提示的一部分。
Just so you're familiar now with some of the vernacular of late.
只是为了让大家熟悉一下近期的术语。
Now, the programming environment that students
现在，学生一直在使用的编程环境被称为Visual Studio
have been using this whole year is known as Visual Studio
Code，一个流行的开源免费产品，大多数
Code, a popular open source, free product, that most--
工程师在使用。
so many engineers around the world now use.
许多工程师在使用。
But we've instrumented it to be a little more course-specific
但我们已经对其进行了调整，使其更具课程特异性，
with some course-specific features that make learning within this environment
具有一些课程特异性功能，使在这个环境中学习
all the easier.
变得更加容易。
It lives at cs50.dev.
它位于cs50.dev。
And as students in this room know, that as of now,
正如这间屋子里的学生所知，目前，
the virtual duck lives within this environment
虚拟鸭子存在于这个环境中，
and can do things like explain highlighted lines of code.
并且可以做一些事情，比如解释高亮的代码行。
So here, for instance, is a screenshot of this programming environment.
所以，这里，例如，是这个编程环境的截图。
Here is some arcane looking code in a language called C, that we've just
这里是一些用C语言写成的看起来很神秘的代码，我们刚刚
left behind us in the class.
在课堂上留下了它。
And suppose that you don't understand what one or more of these lines of code
假设你不理解这些代码行中的一个或多个，
do.
它们的作用。
Students can now highlight those lines, right-click or Control click on it,
学生现在可以高亮这些行，右键单击或按住Control键并单击它，
select explain highlighted code, and voila,
选择“解释高亮代码”，然后，
they see a ChatGPT-like explanation of that very code within a second or so,
他们会看到类似于ChatGPT的解释，解释了这段代码，只需一秒钟左右，
that no human has typed out, but that's been dynamically generated
没有人手动输入，而是动态生成的，
based on this code.
基于这段代码。
Other things that the duck can now do for students
鸭子现在可以为学生做的其他事情
is advise students on how to improve their code style, the aesthetics,
是指导学生如何改进他们的代码风格、美观度，
the formatting thereof.
以及代码的格式。
And so for instance, here is similar code in a language called C.
所以，例如，这里是用C语言编写的类似代码。
And I'll stipulate that it's very messy.
我必须说，它很乱。
Everything is left-aligned instead of nicely indented,
所有内容都左对齐，而不是整齐地缩进，
so it looks a little more structured.
所以它看起来更像结构化的代码。
Students can now click a button.
学生现在可以点击一个按钮。
They'll see at the right-hand side in green
他们将在右侧看到绿色，
how their code should ideally look.
他们的代码应该是什么样的。
And if they're not quite sure what those changes are or why,
如果他们不太确定这些更改是什么或者为什么，
they can click on, explain changes.
他们可以点击“解释更改”。
And similarly, the duck advises them on how and why
同样地，鸭子会建议他们如何以及为什么
to turn their not great code into greater code,
将他们的不太好的代码变成更好的代码，
from left to right respectively.
分别从左到右。
More compellingly and more generalizable beyond CS50 and beyond computer
更引人入胜的是，它更具普遍性，超出了CS50，超出了计算机
science, is AI's ability to answer most of the questions
科学，是AI能够回答学生在线可能提出的大多数问题的能力。
that students might now ask online.
学生可能在线提出的问题。
And we've been doing asynchronous Q&A for years via various mobile or web
多年来，我们一直在通过各种移动或网页应用程序进行异步问答
applications and the like.
等等。
But to date, it has been humans, myself included,
但到目前为止，一直都是人类，包括我自己，
responding to all of those questions.
在回答所有这些问题。
Now the duck has an opportunity to chime in, generally within three seconds,
现在，鸭子有机会插话，通常在三秒钟内，
because we've integrated it into an online Q&A tool
因为我们已经将其整合到在线问答工具中
that students in CS50 and elsewhere across Harvard have long used.
这是哈佛大学 CS50 和其他地方的学生长期以来一直在使用的工具。
So here's an anonymized screenshot of a question from an actual student,
所以这里是一个来自实际学生的匿名截图，
but written here as John Harvard, who asked this summer,
但这里写成约翰·哈佛，他在这个夏天问了这个问题，
in the summer version of CS50, what is flask exactly?
在 CS50 的夏季版本中，什么是烧瓶？
So fairly definitional question.
所以这是一个相当定义性的问题。
And here is what the duck spit out, thanks to that architecture
而这是鸭子吐出的，感谢那架构
I described before.
我之前描述过。
I'll stipulate that this is correct, but it is mostly
我承认这是正确的，但它主要是
a definition, akin to what Google or Bing could already give you last year.
一个定义，类似于 Google 或 Bing 去年已经可以给你的东西。
But here's a more nuanced question, for instance,
但这里有一个更细致的问题，例如，
from another anonymized student.
来自另一位匿名学生。
In this question here, the student's including an error message
在这个问题中，学生包含了一个错误信息
that they're seeing.
他们看到了。
They're asking about that.
他们在问关于这个。
And they're asking a little more broadly and qualitatively, is there
他们问得更广泛和更质化，是否
a more efficient way to write this code, a question that really is best
有一种更有效的方式来写这段代码，一个真正最好的
answered based on experience.
答案是基于经验的。
Here, I'll stipulate that the duck responded with this answer, which
在这里，我承认鸭子用这个答案进行了回复，这
is actually pretty darn good.
实际上非常不错。
Not only responding in English, but with some sample starter code
不仅用英语回复，而且还提供了一些示例入门代码
that would make sense in this context.
在这个上下文中是有意义的。
And at the bottom it's worth noting, because none of this technology
在底部值得注意的是，因为这些技术
is perfect just yet, it's still indeed very bleeding edge,
还没有完美，它仍然非常前沿，
and so what we have chosen to do within CS50 is include disclaimers, like this.
因此，我们在 CS50 中选择做的就是包含免责声明，就像这样。
I am an experimental bot, quack.
我是一个实验性机器人，嘎嘎叫。
Do not assume that my reply is accurate unless you see that it's
不要认为我的回复是准确的，除非你看到它
been endorsed by humans, quack.
得到了人类的认可，嘎嘎叫。
And in fact, at top right, the mechanism we've been using in this tool
事实上，在右上角，我们一直在这个工具中使用的机制
is usually within minutes.
通常在几分钟内。
A human, whether it's a teaching fellow, a course assistant, or myself,
一个人，无论是助教、助教还是我自己，
will click on a button like this to signal to our human students
将点击像这样的按钮来向我们的人类学生发出信号
that yes, like the duck is spot on here, or we have an opportunity, as always,
没错，就像鸭子在这里说的很准确，或者我们一如既往地有机会，
to chime in with our own responses.
用我们自己的答案进行补充。
Frankly, that disclaimer, that button, will soon I do think
坦率地说，那个免责声明，那个按钮，很快我就会认为
go away, as the software gets better and better.
会消失，因为软件会越来越好。
But for now, that's how we're modulating exactly
但目前，这就是我们对学生期望进行精确调整的方式
what students' expectations might be when it
学生对正确性或错误性的期望可能是什么
comes to correctness or incorrectness.
涉及到正确性或错误性。
It's common too in programming, to see a lot of error messages,
在编程中也很常见，看到很多错误信息，
certainly when you're learning first-hand.
尤其是在你亲身学习的时候。
A lot of these error messages are arcane, confusing,
很多错误信息都很晦涩难懂，
certainly to students, versus the people who wrote them.
对于学生来说当然如此，与编写它们的人相比。
Soon students will see a box like this.
很快学生们会看到一个这样的盒子。
Whenever one of their terminal window programs errs,
每当他们的终端窗口程序出错时，
they'll be assisted too with English-like, TF-like support when
他们也会得到类似英语的、类似助教的支持，当
it comes to explaining what it is that went wrong with that command.
涉及到解释那个命令中出了什么问题。
And ultimately, what this is really doing
最终，这实际上是在
for students in our own experience already,
对于我们自己经验中已经有的学生，
is providing them really with virtual office hours and 24/7,
实际上是为他们提供虚拟办公室时间，并且是全天候的，
which is actually quite compelling in a university environment,
这在大学环境中实际上非常有吸引力，
where students' schedules are already tightly packed,
学生的时间表已经非常紧凑，
be it with academics, their curriculars, athletics, and the like--
无论是学术、课程、体育等等，
--and they might have enough time to dive
——他们可能有足够的时间深入
into a homework assignment, maybe eight hours even, for something sizable.
到一个作业中，甚至可能八个小时，为了完成一些比较大的事情。
But if they hit that wall a couple of hours in, yeah,
但如果他们在几个小时后遇到困难，是的，
they can go to office hours or they can ask a question asynchronously online,
他们可以去办公室时间，或者他们可以在线异步提问，
but it's really not optimal in the moment support
但这在那一刻并不是最佳支持
that we can now provide all the more effectively
我们现在可以通过软件更有效地提供
we hope, through software, as well.
我们希望，通过软件，也一样。
So if you're curious.
所以如果你好奇。
Even if you're not a technophile yourself, anyone on the internet
即使你不是一个技术爱好者，任何在互联网上的人
can go to cs50.ai and experiment with this user interface.
都可以去 cs50.ai 并体验这个用户界面。
This one here actually resembles ChatGPT itself, but it's specific to CS50.
这个实际上与 ChatGPT 本身很相似，但它是针对 CS50 的。
And here again is just a sequence of screenshots
这里又是一个截图序列
that I'll stipulate for today's purposes,
为了今天的目的，我承认
are pretty darn good in akin to what I myself or a teaching fellow would reply
非常类似于我自己或助教会回复的内容
to and answer to a student's question, in this case,
并回答学生的问题，在这种情况下，
about their particular code.
关于他们的特定代码。
And ultimately, it's really aspirational.
最终，这真的很有抱负。
The goal here ultimately is to really approximate a one-to-one teacher
这里最终的目标是真正模拟一对一的老师
to student ratio, which despite all of the resources we within CS50,
与学生比例，尽管我们在 CS50 内部拥有所有资源，
we within Harvard and places like Yale have,
我们在哈佛和耶鲁等地方有，
we certainly have never had enough resources
我们当然从来没有足够的资源
to approximate what might really be ideal,
来模拟真正理想的东西，
which is more of an apprenticeship model, a mentorship, whereby it's just
这更像是一种学徒制模式，一种指导，因此它只是
you and that teacher working one-to-one.
你和那个老师一对一地工作。
Now we still have humans, and the goal is not to reduce that human support,
现在我们仍然有人类，目标不是减少这种人力支持，
but to focus it all the more consciously on the students who would benefit most
而是将它更自觉地集中在那些从非个人化的、一对一的支持中获益最多的学生身上
from some impersonal one-to-one support versus students
与那些愿意在一天中的任何时间通过在线方式进行更多数字化的支持的学生相比
who would happily take it at any hour of the day more digitally via online.
他们会很乐意接受。
And in fact, we're still in the process of evaluating just
事实上，我们仍然在评估过程中
how well or not well all of this works.
这一切运行得有多好或不好。
But based on our summer experiment alone with about 70 students
但仅根据我们夏天对大约 70 名学生的实验
a few months back, one student wrote us at term's end it--
几个月前，一个学生在学期结束时给我们写了一封信，内容是——
--"felt like having a personal tutor.
感觉像有了一个私人导师。
I love how AI bots will answer questions without ego and without judgment.
我喜欢 AI 机器人会毫无保留地回答问题，没有自我意识，也没有评判。
Generally entertaining even the stupidest of questions
通常来说，即使是最愚蠢的问题也能娱乐人
without treating them like they're stupid.
并且不会把它们当作蠢问题对待。
It has an, as one could expect," ironically, "an inhuman level
它拥有，正如人们所预料的那样，“讽刺的是，”非人的水平
of patience."
耐心。
And so I thought that's telling as to how even one student is
因此，我认为这说明了，即使是一个学生
perceiving these new possibilities.
也感知到了这些新的可能性。
So let's consider now more academically what
所以现在让我们从学术角度来考虑一下，
it is that's enabling those kinds of tools, not just
是什么让这些工具得以实现，不仅仅是
within CS50, within computer science, but really, the world more generally.
在 CS50 课程中，在计算机科学领域中，而是真正地，更广泛地应用于世界。
What the whole world's been talking about
全世界都在谈论的
is generative artificial intelligence.
是生成式人工智能。
AI that can generate images, generate text, and sort of
可以生成图像、生成文本，并以某种方式
mimic the behavior of what we think of as human.
模仿我们认为人类的行为。
So what does that really mean?
那究竟意味着什么呢？
Well, let's start really at the beginning.
好吧，让我们从一开始真正开始。
Artificial intelligence is actually a technique, a technology,
人工智能实际上是一种技术，
a subject that's actually been with us for some time,
一个我们已经接触了一段时间的学科，
but it really was the introduction of this very user-friendly interface known
但真正重要的是，引入了这个非常人性化的界面，被称为
as ChatGPT.
ChatGPT。
And some of the more recent academic work over really just the past five
而最近在过去五年的学术研究中，
or six years, that really allowed us to take a massive leap forward
或者六年的时间里，真正让我们在技术上取得了巨大的飞跃
it would seem technologically, as to what these things can now do.
看来，在技术上，这些东西现在能做到的事情。
So what is artificial intelligence?
那么什么是人工智能呢？
It's been with us for some time, and it's honestly, so omnipresent,
它已经存在了一段时间，并且老实说，它无处不在，
that we take it for granted nowadays.
以至于我们现在认为它理所当然。
Gmail, Outlook, have gotten really good at spam detection.
Gmail、Outlook 在垃圾邮件检测方面做得越来越好。
If you haven't checked your spam folder in a while,
如果你已经有一段时间没有查看你的垃圾邮件文件夹了，
that's testament to just how good they seem
那就证明了它们似乎是多么地优秀
to be at getting it out of your inbox.
在把垃圾邮件从你的收件箱中清除。
Handwriting recognition has been with us for some time.
手写识别技术已经存在了一段时间了。
I dare say, it, too, is only getting better and better
我敢说，它也只会越来越好
the more the software is able to adapt to different handwriting
随着软件能够适应不同的手写
styles, such as this.
风格，例如像这样。
Recommendation histories and the like, whether you're
推荐历史和其他类似的东西，无论你是在
using Netflix or any other service, have gotten
使用 Netflix 还是任何其他服务，都变得
better and better at recommending things you might like based on things
越来越擅长根据你可能喜欢的以及
you have liked, and maybe based on things
你曾经喜欢的，也许还根据
other people who like the same thing as you might have liked.
其他喜欢和你一样东西的人可能喜欢的东西。
And suffice it to say, there's no one at Netflix
需要说的是，Netflix 上没有人
akin to the old VHS stores of yesteryear,
像过去的老式录像带商店那样，
who are recommending to you specifically what movie you might like.
专门为你推荐你可能喜欢的电影。
And there's no code, no algorithm that says, if they like x, then recommend y,
并且没有代码，没有算法可以这么说，如果他们喜欢 x，就推荐 y，
else recommend z, because there's just too many movies, too many people, too
否则推荐 z，因为电影太多、人太多、
many different tastes in the world.
世界上有太多不同的口味。
So AI is increasingly sort of looking for patterns that might not even
所以人工智能正越来越多地寻找可能甚至
be obvious to us humans, and dynamically figuring out
对我们人类来说并不明显，并动态地找出
what might be good for me, for you or you, or anyone else.
什么可能对我和你，或者任何人都有好处。
Siri, Google Assistant, Alexa, any of these voice recognition tools
Siri、Google Assistant、Alexa，任何这些语音识别工具
that are answering questions.
都能回答问题。
That, too, suffice it to say, is all powered by AI.
需要说的是，这些也都是由人工智能驱动的。
But let's start with something a little simpler than any of those applications.
但是让我们从比任何这些应用都要简单的开始。
And this is one of the first arcade games from yesteryear known as Pong.
这是一款最早的街机游戏，叫做 Pong。
And it's sort of like table tennis.
它有点像乒乓球。
And the person on the left can move their paddle up and down.
左边的人可以上下移动他们的球拍。
Person on the right can do the same.
右边的人也可以这样做。
And the goal is to get the ball past the other person,
目标是让球越过对方，
or conversely, make sure it hits your paddle and bounces back.
或者相反，确保它击中你的球拍并反弹回来。
Well, somewhat simpler than this insofar as it can be one player,
好吧，比这个简单一些，因为它可以是一人游戏，
is another Atari game from yesteryear known
是另一款来自过去年代的雅达利游戏，叫做
as Breakout, whereby you're essentially just trying
Breakout，你基本上就是在尝试
to bang the ball against the bricks to get more and more points
用球击打砖块，获得越来越多的分数
and get rid of all of those bricks.
并消灭掉所有这些砖块。
But all of us in this room probably have a human instinct
但我们房间里的每个人可能都有一个人的本能
for how to win this game, or at least how to play this game.
如何赢得这场比赛，或者至少如何玩这场比赛。
For instance, if the ball pictured here back in the '80s
例如，如果这里图中的球是在 80 年代
as a single red dot just left the paddle, pictured here as a red line,
作为一个红色的点，刚刚离开球拍，这里用一条红线表示，
where is the ball presumably going to go next?
这个球接下来可能会去哪里？
And in turn, which direction should I slide my paddle?
反过来，我应该向哪个方向滑动我的球拍？
To the left or to the right?
向左还是向右？
So presumably, to the left.
所以可以想见，应该是向左。
And we all have an eye for what seemed to be the digital physics of that.
我们都对这种数字物理学有自己的看法。
And indeed, that would then be an algorithm, sort of step
确实，那将是一个算法，一种逐步的
by step instructions for solving some problem.
解决问题的指令。
So how can we now translate that human intuition to what we describe more
那么我们如何将这种人类直觉转化成我们更常描述的
as artificial intelligence?
人工智能呢？
Not nearly as sophisticated as those other applications,
和那些其他应用相比，它并不那么复杂，
but we'll indeed, start with some basics.
但我们确实会从一些基础知识开始。
You might know from economics or strategic thinking or computer science,
你可能从经济学或战略思维或计算机科学中了解到，
this idea of a decision tree that allows you to decide,
决策树的概念，它可以让你决定，
should I go this way or this way when it comes to making a decision.
在做出决定时，我应该走这条路还是那条路。
So let's consider how we could draw a picture to represent even something
所以让我们考虑一下，我们如何画一张图来表示，即使是像
simplistic like Breakout.
Breakout 这样的简单东西。
Well, if the ball is left of the paddle, is a question or a Boolean expression
好吧，如果球在球拍的左边，这是一个问题，或者是一个布尔表达式
I might ask myself in code.
我可能会在代码中问自己。
If yes, then I should move my paddle left, as most everyone just said.
如果是，那么我应该把球拍向左移动，就像大多数人刚刚说的那样。
Else, if the ball is not left of paddle, what do I want to do?
否则，如果球不在球拍的左边，我想要做什么？
Well, I want to ask a question.
好吧，我想要问一个问题。
I don't want to just instinctively go right.
我不想只是本能地向右移动。
I want to check, is the ball to the right of the paddle,
我想要检查，球是否在球拍的右边，
and if yes, well, then yes, go ahead and move the paddle right.
如果可以，那么就移动球拍到右边。
But there is a third situation, which is--
但还有第三种情况，那就是——
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
观众：[听不清]
DAVID J. MALAN: Right.
大卫·马兰：是的。
Like, don't move, it's coming right at you.
就像，别动，它正向你袭来。
So that would be the third scenario here.
所以这将是这里第三种情况。
No, it's not to the right or to the left, so just don't move the paddle.
不，它既不是向右也不是向左，所以就别移动球拍。
You got lucky, and it's coming, for instance, straight down.
你很幸运，它正，例如，直接向下移动。
So Breakout is fairly straightforward when it comes to an algorithm.
所以，当谈到算法时，Breakout 非常直接。
And we can actually translate this as any CS50 student now could,
实际上，任何 CS50 学生现在都可以将它翻译成
to code or pseudocode, sort of English-like code that's independent
代码或伪代码，一种类似英语的代码，独立于
of Java, C, C++ and all of the programming languages of today.
Java、C、C++ 以及当今所有编程语言。
So in English pseudocode, while a game is
因此，在英文伪代码中，当游戏正在
ongoing, if the ball is left of paddle, I should move paddle left.
进行时，如果球在球拍左边，我应该将球拍向左移动。
Else if ball is right of the paddle, it should say paddle, that's a bug,
否则，如果球在球拍右边，它应该说球拍，这是一个错误，
not intended today, move paddle right.
今天不打算移动球拍，将球拍向右移动。
Else, don't move the paddle.
否则，不要移动球拍。
So that, too, represents a translation of this intuition to code
因此，这也代表了这种直觉到代码的翻译
that's very deterministic.
它非常确定性。
You can anticipate all possible scenarios captured in code.
你可以预见代码中包含的所有可能情况。
And frankly, this should be the most boring game of Breakout,
坦率地说，这应该是最无聊的 Breakout 游戏，
because the paddle should just perfectly play this game, assuming
因为球拍应该完美地玩这个游戏，假设
there's no variables or randomness when it comes to speed
速度方面没有变量或随机性
or angles or the like, which real world games certainly try to introduce.
或角度等，而现实世界中的游戏当然会试图引入这些。
But let's consider another game from yesteryear
但是，让我们考虑一下另一个来自过去的游戏
that you might play with your kids today or you did yourself growing up.
你可能今天会和你的孩子们一起玩，或者你小时候玩过。
Here's tic-tac-toe.
这是井字棋。
And for those unfamiliar, the goal is to get three O's in a row
对于那些不熟悉的人来说，目标是在一行中得到三个 O
or three X's in a row, vertically, horizontally, or diagonally.
或三个 X 在一行，垂直、水平或对角线。
So suppose it's now X's turn.
假设现在轮到 X 了。
If you've played tic-tac-toe, most of you
如果你玩过井字棋，你们大多数人
probably just have an immediate instinct as to where X should probably go,
可能本能地知道 X 应该去哪里，
so that it doesn't lose instantaneously.
这样它就不会立刻输掉。
But let's consider in the more general case, how do you solve tic-tac-toe.
但让我们在更一般的情况下考虑一下，如何解决井字棋。
Frankly, if you're in the habit of losing tic-tac-toe,
坦率地说，如果你习惯输井字棋，
but you're not trying to lose tic-tac-toe,
但你并没有试图输掉井字棋，
you're actually playing it wrong.
你实际上玩错了。
Like, you should minimally be able to always force a tie in tic-tac-toe.
就像，你至少应该能够在井字棋中始终迫使平局。
And better yet, you should be able to beat the other person.
而且更好的是，你应该能够击败对方。
So hopefully, everyone now will soon walk away with this strategy.
因此，希望每个人很快就能掌握这种策略。
So how can we borrow inspiration from those same decision trees
那么，我们如何从那些相同的决策树中借鉴灵感
and do something similar here?
在这里做类似的事情？
So if you, the player, ask yourself, can I get three in a row on this turn?
所以，如果你，玩家，问自己，我这一回合能得到三个连线吗？
Well, if yes, then you should do that and play the X in that position.
如果可以，那么你应该这样做，并将 X 放在那个位置。
Play in the square to get three in a row.
将 X 放在那个方格中，以得到三个连线。
Straight forward.
非常直接。
If you can't get three in a row in this turn, you should ask another question.
如果你这一回合不能得到三个连线，你应该问另一个问题。
Can my opponent get three in a row in their next turn?
我的对手下一回合能得到三个连线吗？
Because then you better preempt that by moving into that position.
因为那样你最好通过移动到那个位置来阻止它。
Play in the square to block opponent's three in a row.
将 X 放在那个方格中，以阻止对手的三个连线。
What if though, that's not the case, right?
但是，如果情况并非如此呢？
What if there aren't even that many X's and O's on the board?
如果棋盘上甚至没有那么多的 X 和 O 呢？
If you're in the habit of just kind of playing
如果你习惯了那种随机玩
randomly, like you might not be playing optimally as a good AI could.
的方式，就像你可能没有像一个好的 AI 那样最佳地玩游戏。
So if no, it's kind of a question mark.
所以如果不能，这就像一个问号。
In fact, there's probably more to this tree,
事实上，这棵树可能还有更多，
because we could think through, what if I go there.
因为我们可以思考，如果我走到那里。
Wait a minute, what if I go there or there or there?
等一下，如果我走到那里或那里或那里呢？
You can start to think a few steps ahead as a computer could do much better even
你可以开始向前思考几步，就像一台计算机可以做得更好，甚至比
than us humans.
我们人类还要好。
So suppose, for instance, it's O's turn.
假设，例如，现在轮到 O 了。
Now those of you who are very good at tic-tac-toe
现在，你们中那些非常擅长井字棋的人
might have an instinct for where to go.
可能本能地知道应该去哪里。
But this is an even harder problem, it would seem.
但这个问题似乎更难。
I could go in eight possible places if I'm O.
如果我是 O，我可以走到八个可能的位置。
But let's try to break that down more algorithmically, as in AI would.
但让我们尝试用算法的方式来分解它，就像 AI 一样。
And let's recognize, too, that with games in particular, one of the reasons
而且，让我们也认识到，尤其是在游戏中，AI 能够早期被采用来对抗 CPU 的原因之一是，
that AI was so early adopted in these games, playing the CPU,
游戏非常适合被定义，
is that games really lend themselves to defining them,
如果将游戏从数学角度上变得不再有趣，
if taking the fun out of it mathematically.
将其定义为输入和输出，例如球拍向左或向右移动，球向上或向下移动。
Defining them in terms of inputs and outputs, maybe paddle moving
你可以在一个非常无聊的低级别上对它进行量化。
left or right, ball moving up or down.
但这有助于我们最佳地解决它。
You can really quantize it at a very boring low level.
事实上，在大多数游戏中，目标是最大化或最小化某个数学函数，对吧？
But that lends itself then to solving it optimally.
大多数游戏，如果你有分数，目标是最大化你的分数，
And in fact, with most games, the goal is to maximize or maybe
实际上，要获得高分。
minimize some math function, right?
因此，游戏适合很好地转换为数学，
Most games, if you have scores, the goal is to maximize your score,
进而适用于 AI 解决方案。
and indeed, get a high score.
因此，人们可能会在算法和人工智能课程中学习到的第一个算法是
So games lend themselves to a nice translation to mathematics,
被称为 minimax 的算法，它暗示着尝试
and in turn here, AI solutions.
最大化或最小化某些内容作为你的函数，你的目标。
So one of the first algorithms one might learn in a class on algorithms
它实际上是从我们一直在讨论的那些决策树中获得灵感的。
and on artificial intelligence is something
但首先，定义一下。
called minimax, which alludes to this idea of trying
这里有三个典型的井字棋棋盘。
to minimize and/or maximize something as your function, your goal.
这是 O 获胜的棋盘，绿色部分表示获胜的三个连线。
And it actually derives its inspiration from these same decision trees
这是 X 获胜的棋盘，绿色部分表示获胜的三个连线。
that we've been talking about.
这是平局的棋盘。
But first, a definition.
Here are three representative tic-tac-toe boards.
Here is one in which O has clearly won, per the green.
Here is one in which X has clearly won, per the green.
And this one in the middle just represents a draw.
Now, there's a bunch of other ways that tic-tac-toe could end, but here's
现在，井字棋可能以很多其他方式结束，但是这里
just three representative ones.
只是三个代表性的例子。
But let's make tic-tac-toe even more boring
但让我们让井字棋变得更加无聊
than it might have always struck you as.
比你一直认为的还要无聊。
Let's propose that this kind of configuration
让我们假设这种配置
should have a score of negative 1.
应该有一个负1的得分。
If O wins, it's a negative 1.
如果O获胜，它就是负1。
If X wins, it's a positive 1.
如果X获胜，它就是正1。
And if no one wins, we'll call it a 0.
如果没有人获胜，我们将把它称为0。
We need some way of talking about and reasoning about which of these outcomes
我们需要一些方法来谈论和推理这些结果中的哪一个
is better than the other.
比另一个更好。
And what's simpler than 0, 1 and negative 1?
还有什么比0、1和负1更简单的？
So the goal though, of X, it would seem, is
所以X的目标，似乎是
to maximize its score, but the goal of O is to minimize its score.
最大化它的得分，但O的目标是最小化它的得分。
So X is really trying to get positive 1, O is really trying to get negative 1.
所以X实际上是在尝试获得正1，O实际上是在尝试获得负1。
And no one really wants 0, but that's better than losing to the other person.
而且没有人真正想要0，但这比输给另一个人要好。
So we have now a way to define what it means to win or lose.
所以我们现在有了一种方法来定义获胜或失败的含义。
Well, now we can employ a strategy here.
好了，现在我们可以在这里运用策略。
Here, just as a quick check, what would the score be of this board?
这里，只是一个快速检查，这个棋盘的得分是多少？
Just so everyone's on the same page.
为了让每个人都处于同一页。
AUDIENCE: 1.
观众：1。
DAVID J. MALAN: Or, so 1, because X has one and we just stipulated arbitrarily,
大卫·马兰：或者说1，因为X有一个，而且我们只是任意规定，
this means that this board has a value of 1.
这意味着这个棋盘的值为1。
Now let's put it into a more interesting context.
现在让我们把它放在一个更有趣的背景下。
Here, a game has been played for a few moves already.
这里，游戏已经进行了几步了。
There's two spots left.
还有两个位置剩下。
No one has won just yet.
目前还没有人获胜。
And suppose that it's O's turn now.
假设现在轮到O了。
Now, everyone probably has an instinct already as to where to go,
现在，每个人可能已经有一种本能，知道应该往哪里走，
but let's try to break this down more algorithmically.
但让我们尝试更算法地分析一下。
So what is the value of this board?
那么这个棋盘的值是多少？
Well, we don't know yet, because no one has won,
好吧，我们还不知道，因为还没有人获胜，
so let's consider what could happen next.
所以让我们考虑一下接下来会发生什么。
So we can draw this actually as a tree, as before.
所以我们可以像以前一样把它画成一棵树。
Here, for instance, is what might happen if O
例如，这里可能发生的事情是O
goes into the top left-hand corner.
进入左上角。
And here's what might happen if O goes into the bottom middle spot instead.
而这里可能发生的事情是O进入底部中间的位置。
We should ask ourselves, what's the value of this board, what's
我们应该问问自己，这个棋盘的值是多少？
the value of this board?
这个棋盘的值是多少？
Because if O's purpose in life is to minimize its score,
因为如果O生命中的目标是最小化它的得分，
it's going to go left or right based on whichever yields the smallest number.
它将会根据哪个产生最小的数字而向左或向右走。
Negative 1, ideally.
理想情况下是负1。
But we're still not sure yet, because we don't have definitions for boards
但我们仍然不确定，因为我们还没有定义带有洞的棋盘
with holes in them like this.
像这样的棋盘。
So what could happen next here?
那么接下来这里会发生什么？
Well, it's obviously going to be X's turn next.
好吧，显然轮到X了。
So if X moves, unfortunately, X has one in this configuration.
所以如果X移动，不幸的是，在这种配置中X有一个。
We can now conclude that the value of this board is what number?
我们现在可以得出结论，这个棋盘的值是多少？
AUDIENCE: 1.
观众：1。
DAVID J. MALAN: So 1.
大卫·马兰：所以是1。
And because there's only one way to reach this board, by transitivity,
而且因为只有一条路径可以到达这个棋盘，通过传递性，
you might as well think of the value of this previous board as also 1,
你也可以认为这个先前棋盘的值也是1，
because no matter what, it's going to lead to that same outcome.
因为无论如何，它都会导致相同的结果。
And so the value of this board is actually still to be determined,
所以这个棋盘的值实际上仍然有待确定，
because we don't know if O is going to want to go with the 1,
因为我们不知道O是否想要选择1，
and probably not, because that means X wins.
而且很可能不会，因为这意味着X获胜。
But let's see what the value of this board is.
但让我们看看这个棋盘的值是多少。
Well, suppose that indeed, X goes in that top left corner here.
好吧，假设X真的进入了左上角。
What's the value of this board here?
这里这个棋盘的值是多少？
0, because no one has won.
0，因为没有人获胜。
There's no X's or O's three in a row.
没有X或O三个连成一排。
So the value of this board is 0.
所以这个棋盘的值是0。
There's only one way logically to get there,
从逻辑上来说，只有一条路径可以到达那里，
so we might as well think of the value of this board as also 0.
所以我们也可以认为这个棋盘的值也是0。
And so now, what's the value of this board?
所以现在，这个棋盘的值是多少？
Well, if we started the story by thinking about O's turn,
好吧，如果我们从思考O的回合开始，
O's purpose is the min in minimax, then which move is O going to make?
O的目标是在极小极大算法中取最小值，那么O会走哪一步？
Go to the left or go to the right?
向左走还是向右走？
O's was probably going to go to the right
O很可能会向右走
and make the move that leads to, whoops, that leads to this board,
并走一步导致，哎呀，导致了这个棋盘，
because even though O can't win in this configuration, at least X didn't win.
因为即使O在这种配置中无法获胜，至少X也没有获胜。
So it's minimized its score relatively, even though it's not a clean win.
所以它相对地最小化了它的得分，即使它没有完全获胜。
Now, this is all fine and good for a configuration
现在，这对棋盘的配置来说都很好
of the board that's like almost done.
几乎快要结束的棋盘。
There's only two moves left.
只剩下两个回合了。
The game's about to end.
游戏即将结束。
But if you kind of expand in your mind's eye,
但如果你在脑海中扩展一下，
how did we get to this branch of the decision tree,
我们是如何到达决策树的这个分支的，
if we rewind one step where there's three possible moves,
如果我们倒退一步，那里有三个可能的移动，
frankly, the decision tree is a lot bigger.
坦白地说，决策树要大得多。
If we rewind further in your mind's eye and have four moves
如果我们在脑海中进一步倒退，并且有四个回合
left or five moves or all nine moves left,
剩下，或者五个回合，或者九个回合都剩下，
imagine just zooming out, out, and out.
想象一下只是不断地缩小，缩小，缩小。
This is becoming a massive, massive tree of decisions.
这正在变成一棵巨大无比的决策树。
Now, even so, here is that same subtree, the same decision tree
现在，即使如此，这里也是同一棵子树，同一棵决策树
we just looked at.
我们刚刚看过的。
This is the exact same thing, but I shrunk the font so
这是完全相同的东西，但我缩小了字体，所以
that it appears here on the screen here.
它出现在屏幕上的这里。
But over here, we have what could happen if instead,
但这里，我们有如果相反，会发生什么，
it's actually X's turn, because we're one move prior.
实际上轮到X了，因为我们提前一步。
There's a bunch of different moves X could now make, too.
X现在也可以进行很多不同的移动。
So what is the implication of this?
那么这意味着什么呢？
Well, most humans are not thinking through tic-tac-toe to this extreme.
好吧，大多数人不会对井字棋进行如此深入的思考。
And frankly, most of us probably just don't have the mental capacity
而且坦白地说，我们大多数人可能只是没有这样的心智能力
to think about going left and then right and then left and then right.
去思考先向左走，然后向右走，再向左走，然后向右走。
Right?
对吧？
This is not how people play tic-tac-toe.
这不是人们玩井字棋的方式。
Like, we're not using that much memory, so to speak.
也就是说，我们没有使用那么多的内存。
But a computer can handle that, and computers
但电脑可以处理这些，而且电脑
can play tic-tac-toe optimally.
可以最佳地玩井字棋。
So if you're beating a computer at tic-tac-toe, like,
所以如果你在井字棋中打败了电脑，就像
it's not implemented very well.
它没有很好地实现。
It's not following this very logical, deterministic minimax algorithm.
它没有遵循这种非常逻辑的确定性极小极大算法。
But this is where now AI is no longer as simple as just
但现在 AI 不再像以前一样简单，仅仅是
doing what these decision trees say.
做这些决策树所说的。
In the context of tic-tac-toe, here's how we might translate this
在井字棋的语境下，这就是我们可能将其翻译成代码的方式，例如。
to code, for instance.
例如。
If player is X, for each possible move, calculate
如果玩家是 X，对于每个可能的移动，计算
a score for the board, as we were doing verbally,
棋盘的得分，正如我们之前口头所说，
and then choose the move with the highest score.
然后选择得分最高的移动。
Because X's goal is to maximize its score.
因为 X 的目标是最大化它的得分。
If the player is O, though, for each possible move,
如果玩家是 O，那么对于每个可能的移动，
calculate a score for the board, and then
计算棋盘的得分，然后
choose the move with the lowest score.
选择得分最低的移动。
So that's a distillation of that verbal walkthrough
所以这是对那个口头演练的提炼
into what CS50 students know now as code, or at least pseudocode.
成为 CS50 学生现在所知的代码，或者至少是伪代码。
But the problem with games, not so much tic-tac-toe, but other more
但问题在于游戏，不是井字棋，而是其他更
sophisticated games is this.
复杂的游戏是这样的。
Does anyone want to ballpark how many possible ways there
有人想估算一下有多少种可能的方式
are to play tic-tac-toe?
来玩井字棋吗？
Paper, pencil, two human children, how many different ways?
纸，铅笔，两个孩子，有多少种不同的方式？
How long could you keep them occupied playing tic-tac-toe in different ways?
你能用不同的方式让他们玩多久的井字棋？
If you actually think through, how big does this tree get,
如果你真正思考一下，这棵树会变得有多大，
how many leaves are there on this decision tree, like how many
这棵决策树上有多少叶子，就像有多少
different directions, well, if you're thinking 255,168, you are correct.
不同的方向，好吧，如果你在想 255,168，你是正确的。
And now most of us in our lifetime have probably not
而且我们大多数人可能一生都没有
played tic-tac-toe that many times.
玩过那么多次的井字棋。
So think about how many games you've been missing out on.
所以想想你错过了多少游戏。
There are different decisions you could have been making all these years.
这些年来你本可以做出不同的决定。
Now, that's a big number, but honestly, that's not a big number for a computer.
现在，这是一个很大的数字，但说实话，对于电脑来说，这不是一个很大的数字。
That's a few megabytes of memory maybe, to keep all of that in mind
也许只需要几兆字节的内存，就可以将所有这些都记在心中
and implement that kind of code in C or Java or C++ or something else.
并在 C 或 Java 或 C++ 或其他语言中实现这种代码。
But other games are much more complicated.
但其他游戏则复杂得多。
And the games that you and I might play as we get older,
我们随着年龄增长可能会玩的游戏，
they include maybe chess.
可能包括象棋。
And if you think about chess with only the first four moves, back and forth
如果你考虑一下象棋，只有前四个回合，来回
four times, so only four moves.
四次，所以只有四个回合。
That's not even a very long game.
这甚至不是一个很长的游戏。
Anyone want a ballpark how many different ways
有人想估算一下有多少种不同的方式
there are to begin a game of chess with four moves back and forth?
来开始一场象棋游戏，来回四个回合？
This is evidence as to why chess is apparently so hard.
这是为什么象棋显然如此困难的证据。
288 million ways, which is why when you are really good at chess,
有 2.88 亿种方式，这就是为什么当你真的很擅长象棋的时候，
you are really good at chess.
你真的很擅长象棋。
Because apparently, you either have an intuition for
因为看来，你要么对
or a mind for thinking it would seem so many more steps ahead
或者对思考，看起来你会提前很多步
than your opponent.
比你的对手。
And don't get us started on something like Go.
而且别让我们开始讨论像围棋这样的东西。
266 quintillion ways to play Go's first four moves.
围棋的前四个回合有 266 quintillion 种方式。
So at this point, we just can't pull out our Mac, our PC,
所以在这个阶段，我们无法拿出我们的 Mac，我们的 PC，
certainly not our phone, to solve optimally games like chess and Go,
当然也无法拿出我们的手机，来最佳地解决像象棋和围棋这样的游戏，
because we don't have big enough CPUs.
因为我们没有足够大的 CPU。
We don't have enough memory.
我们没有足够的内存。
We don't have enough years in our lifetimes for the computers
我们没有足够的人生年限让电脑
to crunch all of those numbers.
来处理所有这些数字。
And thus was born a different form of AI that's
因此，一种不同的 AI 形式诞生了，它
more inspired by finding patterns more dynamically,
更多地受到动态查找模式的启发，
learning from data, as opposed to being told by humans, here
从数据中学习，而不是被人类告知，这里
is the code via which to solve this problem.
是解决这个问题的代码。
So machine learning is a subset of artificial intelligence
因此机器学习是人工智能的一个子集
that tries instead to get machines to learn
它试图让机器学习
what they should do without being so coached step by step by step by humans
它们应该做什么，而不需要人类一步一步地指导
here.
这里。
Reinforcement learning, for instance, is one such example thereof,
例如，强化学习就是这样一个例子，
wherein reinforcement learning, you sort of wait
在强化学习中，你有点像在等待
for the computer or maybe a robot to maybe just get
电脑或者机器人可能只是变得
better and better and better at things.
越来越擅长某些事情。
And as it does, you reward it with a reward function.
当它做到的时候，你会用一个奖励函数来奖励它。
Give it plus 1 every time it does something well.
每次它做得好就给它加 1 分。
And maybe minus 1.
也许减 1 分。
You punish it any time it does something poorly.
每次它做不好就惩罚它。
And if you simply program this AI or this robot to maximize its score,
如果你只是简单地编程这个 AI 或这个机器人来最大化它的得分，
never mind minimizing, maximize its score,
不要管最小化，最大化它的得分，
ideally, it should repeat behaviors that got it plus 1.
理想情况下，它应该重复那些让它得到加 1 分的行为。
It should decrease the frequency with which it does
它应该减少它进行
bad behaviors that got it negative 1.
那些让它得到减 1 分的错误行为的频率。
And you can reinforce this kind of learning.
你可以强化这种学习。
In fact, I have here one demonstration.
事实上，我这里有一个演示。
Could a student come on up who does not think
有学生愿意上来吗？他们不认为自己
they are particularly coordinated?
特别协调。
If-- OK, wow, you're being nominated by your friends.
如果——好的，哇，你被你的朋友提名了。
Come on up.
上来吧。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
Their hands went up instantly for you.
他们的手瞬间举了起来，为你。
OK, what is your name?
好的，你叫什么名字？
AMAKA: My name's Amaka.
AMAKA: 我叫 Amaka。
DAVID J. MALAN: Amaka, do you want to introduce yourself to the world?
DAVID J. MALAN: Amaka，你想向全世界介绍一下你自己吗？
AMAKA: Hi, my name is Amaka.
AMAKA: 嗨，我叫 Amaka。
I am a first year in Holworthy.
我是一年级学生，住在 Holworthy。
I'm planning to concentrate in CS.
我计划专注于 CS。
DAVID J. MALAN: Wonderful.
DAVID J. MALAN: 太棒了。
Nice to see you.
很高兴见到你。
Come on over here.
过来这边。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
So, yes, oh, no, it's sort of like a game show here.
是的，哦，不，这有点像一个游戏节目。
We have a pan here with what appears to be something pancake-like.
这里有一个平底锅，里面似乎有一些像煎饼一样的东西。
And we'd like to teach you how to flip a pancake,
我们想教你如何翻煎饼，
so that when you gesture upward, the pancake should flip around
这样当你向上示意的时候，煎饼就会翻转过来
as though you cooked the other side.
就像你把另一面煎熟了一样。
So we're going to reward you verbally with plus 1 or minus 1.
所以我们将用“加1”或“减1”来口头奖励你。
Minus 1.
减1。
OK, plus 1!
好的，加1！
Plus 1, so do more of that.
加1，所以多做点。
Minus 1.
减1。
Do less of that.
少做点。
[LAUGHTER]
[笑声]
AUDIENCE: Great, great.
观众：太棒了，太棒了。
DAVID J. MALAN: All right!
戴维·马兰：好的！
A big round of applause.
热烈的掌声。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
Thank you.
谢谢。
We've been in the habit of handing out Super Mario Brothers Oreos this year,
今年我们一直习惯于赠送超级马里奥兄弟奥利奥饼干，
so thank you for participating.
所以感谢你们的参与。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
So, this is actually a good example of an opportunity
所以，这实际上是一个很好的机会，
for reinforcement learning.
用于强化学习。
And wonderfully, a researcher has posted a video that we thought we'd share.
很棒的是，一位研究人员发布了一段视频，我们想分享给大家。
It's about a minute and a half long, where
它大约一分钟半长，在那里
you can watch a robot now do exactly what our wonderful human volunteer here
你可以看到一个机器人现在正在做的事情，与我们这里这位很棒的人类志愿者完全一样
just attempted as well.
也尝试过。
So let me go ahead and play this on the screen
所以让我继续在屏幕上播放
and give you a sense of what the human and the robot are doing together.
让你了解一下人类和机器人正在一起做什么。
So their pancake looks a little similar there.
所以他们的煎饼在那里看起来很相似。
The human here is going to first sort of train the robot what
这里的人类将首先训练机器人
to do by showing it some gestures.
通过展示一些手势来做些什么。
But there's no one right way to do this.
但这没有一种正确的方法。
But the human seems to know how to do it pretty well in this case,
但在这种情况下，人类似乎知道如何做得很好，
and so it's trying to give the machine examples
因此，它正试图给机器一些例子
of how to flip a pancake successfully.
如何成功地翻煎饼。
But now, this is the very first trial.
但现在，这是第一次尝试。
OK, look familiar?
好的，看起来眼熟吗？
You're in good company.
你和大家一样。
After three trials.
三次尝试后。
[CLANG]
[叮当]
[PLOP]
[噗通]
OK.
好的。
[CLANG]
[叮当]
[PLOP]
[噗通]
OK.
好的。
Now 10 tries.
现在是10次尝试。
There's the human picking up the pancake.
那是人类拿起煎饼。
After 11 trials--
11次尝试后——
[CLANG]
[叮当]
[PLOP]
[噗通]
And meanwhile, there's presumably a human coding this,
与此同时，应该有人在编写代码，
in the sense that someone is saying good job or bad job, plus 1 or minus 1.
从某种意义上说，有人会说“干得好”或“干得不好”，“加1”或“减1”。
20 trials.
20次尝试。
Here now we'll see how the computer knows what it's even doing.
现在我们将看到计算机是如何知道它在做什么的。
There's just a mapping to some kind of XYZ coordinate system.
这只是一个映射到某种 XYZ 坐标系。
So the robot can quantize what it is it's doing.
所以机器人可以量化它正在做的事情。
Nice!
不错！
To do more of one thing, less of another.
多做一些事情，少做一些事情。
And you're just seeing a visualization in the background
你只是看到背景中可视化的东西
of those digitized movements.
那些数字化动作。
And so now, after 50 some odd trials, the robot, too, has got it spot on.
所以现在，经过 50 多次尝试，机器人也做对了。
And it should be able to repeat this again and again
它应该能够一遍又一遍地重复
and again, in order to keep flipping this pancake.
一次又一次地重复，以便继续翻转这个煎饼。
So our human volunteer wonderfully took you even fewer trials.
所以，我们的人类志愿者非常出色地让你只用了更少的尝试。
But this is an example then, to be clear,
但这是一个例子，需要明确的是，
of what we'd call reinforcement learning,
我们称之为强化学习，
whereby you're reinforcing a behavior you want or negatively reinforcing.
即强化你想要的某种行为，或负面强化。
That is, punishing a behavior that you don't.
也就是说，惩罚你不想要的某种行为。
Here's another example that brings us back
这里还有一个例子，让我们回到
into the realm of games a little bit, but in a very abstract way.
游戏领域，但以一种非常抽象的方式。
If we were playing a game like The Floor Is Lava,
如果我们在玩像“地板是熔岩”这样的游戏，
where you're only supposed to step certain places so that you don't
你应该只在某些地方踩，这样你才不会
fall straight in the lava pit or something like that and lose a point
直接掉进熔岩坑，或者类似的事情，然后失去一分
or lose a life, each of these squares might represent a position.
或者失去一条生命，这些方格中的每一个都可能代表一个位置。
This yellow dot might represent the human player that can go up, down,
这个黄点可能代表人类玩家，可以向上、向下，
left or right within this world.
向左或向右在这个世界里移动。
I'm revealing to the whole audience where the lava pits are.
我向所有观众展示了熔岩坑在哪里。
But the goal for this yellow dot is to get to green.
但这个黄点的目标是到达绿色。
But the yellow dot, as in any good game, does not have this bird's eye view
但黄点，就像在任何好的游戏中一样，没有鸟瞰视角
and knows from the get-go exactly where to go.
并且一开始就确切地知道该去哪里。
It's going to have to try some trial and error.
它将不得不尝试一些试错法。
But if we, the programmers, maybe reinforce good behavior
但是，如果我们，程序员，也许强化良好的行为
or punish bad behavior, we can teach this yellow dot,
或者惩罚不良行为，我们可以教这个黄点，
without giving it step by step, up, down,
在不告诉它一步一步，向上、向下，
left, right instructions, what behaviors to repeat
向左、向右的指令的情况下，什么行为需要重复
and what behaviors not to repeat.
以及什么行为不需要重复。
So, for instance, suppose the robot moves right.
所以，例如，假设机器人向右移动。
Ah, that was bad.
啊，那很糟糕。
You fell in the lava already, so we'll use a bit of computer memory
你已经掉进熔岩了，所以我们将使用一些计算机内存
to draw a thicker red line there.
在那里画一条更粗的红线。
Don't do that again.
不要再那样做了。
So, negative 1, so to speak.
所以，可以这么说，减1。
Maybe the yellow dot moves up next time.
也许下次黄点会向上移动。
We can reward that behavior by not drawing any walls
我们可以通过不画任何墙壁来奖励这种行为
and allowing it to go again.
并让它再次移动。
It's making pretty good progress, but, oh, darn it, it took a right turn
它取得了很好的进展，但是，哦，糟糕，它向右转了。
and now fell into the lava.
现在掉进了熔岩里。
But let's use a bit more of the computer's memory
但让我们多使用一点计算机的内存
and keep track of the, OK, do not do that thing anymore.
并跟踪，好的，不要再做那件事了。
Maybe the next time the human dot goes this way.
也许下次人点朝这个方向走。
Oh, we want to punish that behavior, so we'll
哦，我们想惩罚这种行为，所以我们会
remember as much with that red line.
用那条红线记住尽可能多的东西。
But now we're starting to make progress until, oh, now we hit this one.
但现在我们开始取得进展，直到，哦，现在我们撞到这个了。
And eventually, even though the yellow dot, much like our human,
最终，尽管黄点，就像我们人类一样，
much like our pancake flipping robot had to try again and again and again,
就像我们的煎饼翻转机器人一样，不得不一次又一次地尝试，
after enough trials, it's going to start to realize what behaviors it should
经过足够的尝试，它将开始意识到它应该重复哪些行为
repeat and which ones it shouldn't.
以及哪些不应该重复。
And so in this case, maybe it finally makes its way up to the green dot.
因此在这种情况下，也许它终于到达了绿点。
And just to recap, once it finds that path,
为了回顾一下，一旦它找到了那条路径，
now it can remember it forever as with these green thicker lines.
现在它可以永远记住它，就像这些绿色的粗线一样。
Any time you want to leave this map, any time you get really good
任何时候你想离开这张地图，任何时候你玩得非常好了
at the Nintendo game, you follow that same path again and again,
在任天堂游戏里，你会一次又一次地走同一条路，
so you don't fall into the lava.
这样你就不会掉进熔岩里。
But an astute human observer might realize that, yes, this is correct.
但一位敏锐的人类观察者可能会意识到，是的，这是正确的。
It's getting out of this so-called maze.
它正在走出这个所谓的迷宫。
But what is suboptimal or bad about this solution?
但是这个解决方案有什么不好或不理想的地方呢？
Sure.
当然。
AUDIENCE: It's taking a really long time.
观众：它花了很长时间。
It's not the most efficient way to get there.
这不是到达那里的最有效方式。
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
大卫·马兰：没错。
It's taking a really long time.
它花了很长时间。
An inefficient way to get there, because I dare say,
一种低效的到达那里方式，因为我敢说，
if we just tried a different path occasionally,
如果我们偶尔尝试不同的路径，
maybe we could get lucky and get to the exit quicker.
也许我们可以走运，更快地到达出口。
And maybe that means we get a higher score or we get rewarded even more.
也许这意味着我们可以获得更高的分数，或者获得更多奖励。
So within a lot of artificial intelligence algorithms,
因此，在许多人工智能算法中，
there's this idea of exploring versus exploiting,
有一个探索与利用的概念，
whereby you should occasionally, yes, exploit the knowledge you already have.
也就是说，你应该偶尔，是的，利用你已经拥有的知识。
And in fact, frequently exploit that knowledge.
事实上，经常利用这些知识。
But occasionally you know what you should probably do,
但偶尔你应该知道你应该做的事情，
is explore just a little bit.
就是探索一点点。
Take a left instead of a right and see if it leads you to the solution
向左走而不是向右走，看看它是否能更快地让你找到解决方案
even more quickly.
甚至更快。
And you might find a better and better solution.
你可能会找到越来越好的解决方案。
So here mathematically is how we might think of this.
所以，从数学角度来看，我们可能会这样思考。
10% of the time we might say that epsilon, just some variable, sort
我们可能会说 10% 的时间，epsilon，只是一个变量，某种程度
of a sprinkling of salt into the algorithm here, epsilon
就像往这里的算法里撒一点盐，epsilon
will be like 10% of the time.
就像 10% 的时间一样。
So if my robot or my player picks a random number that's less than 10%,
所以，如果我的机器人或我的玩家选择了一个小于 10% 的随机数，
that's going to make a random move.
它将会随机行动。
Go left instead of right, even if you really typically go right.
向左走而不是向右走，即使你通常真的向右走。
Otherwise, guys make the move with the highest value,
否则，伙计们会做出具有最高价值的行动，
as we've learned over time.
正如我们随着时间的推移所了解的那样。
And what the robot might learn then, is that we could actually
而机器人可能学到的就是，我们实际上可以
go via this path, which gets us to the output faster.
通过这条路径走，这样我们可以更快地到达输出。
We get a higher score, we do it in less time, it's a win-win.
我们得到了更高的分数，我们花更少的时间，这是一个双赢。
Frankly, this really resonates with me, because I've
坦白地说，这真的引起了我的共鸣，因为我
been in the habit, as maybe some of you are, when you go to a restaurant maybe
习惯了，也许你们中的一些人也是这样，当你也许去一家餐厅
that you really like, you find a dish you really like--
你真的很喜欢，你发现了一道你真的很喜欢的菜--
--I will never again know what other dishes that restaurant
--我永远不会再知道那家餐厅还有哪些其他菜肴
offers, because I'm locally optimally happy with the dish I've chosen.
提供，因为我对目前选择的菜肴感到很满意。
And I will never know if there's an even better dish at that restaurant
我永远不会知道那家餐厅是否还有更好的菜肴
unless again, I sort of sprinkle a little bit of epsilon,
除非，再一次，我撒一些 epsilon，
a little bit of randomness into my game playing, my dining out.
在我的游戏玩法中，我的外出就餐中，撒一些随机性。
The catch, of course, though, is that I might be punished.
当然，问题是，我可能会受到惩罚。
I might, therefore, be less happy if I pick something and I don't like it.
因此，如果我选择了一些我不喜欢的，我可能会不那么高兴。
So there's this tension between exploring and exploiting.
所以，探索与利用之间存在着这种张力。
But in general in computer science, and especially in AI,
但总的来说，在计算机科学，尤其是人工智能中，
adding a little bit of randomness, especially over time,
添加一点点随机性，尤其是在一段时间内，
can, in fact, yield better and better outcomes.
事实上，可以产生越来越好的结果。
But now there's this notion all the more of deep learning,
但现在，深度学习的概念越来越突出，
whereby you're trying to infer, to detect patterns,
它试图推断，检测模式，
figure out how to solve problems, even if the AI has never
找出如何解决问题，即使人工智能从未
seen those problems before, and even if there's no human there to reinforce
见过这些问题，即使没有人在那里加强
positive or negatively behavior.
正面或负面行为。
Maybe it's just too complex of a problem for a human
也许对于人类来说，这是一个过于复杂的问题
to stand alongside the robot and say, good or bad job.
无法站在机器人旁边说，做得好或做得不好。
So with deep learning, they're actually very much related
因此，深度学习实际上与
to what you might know as neural networks, inspired by human physiology,
你可能知道的神经网络密切相关，它受到人类生理学的启发，
whereby inside of our brains and elsewhere in our body,
也就是说，在我们的大脑和其他身体部位，
there's lots of these neurons here that can
这里有很多神经元，它们可以
send electrical signals to make movements
发送电信号来产生动作
happen from brain to extremities.
从大脑到四肢发生。
You might have two of these via which signals can
你可能有两个，通过它信号可以
be transmitted over a larger distance.
在更长的距离上传输。
And so computer scientists for some time have drawn inspiration
因此，计算机科学家很长一段时间以来一直从
from these neurons to create in software, what we call neural networks.
这些神经元中获得灵感，在软件中创造了我们称为神经网络的东西。
Whereby, there's inputs to these networks
也就是说，这些网络有输入
and there's outputs from these networks that represents inputs
还有来自这些网络的输出，它表示输入
to problems and solutions thereto.
到问题以及对这些问题的解决方案。
So let me abstract away the more biological diagrams
所以，让我用更抽象的生物图
with just circles that represent nodes, or neurons, in this case.
只用圆圈来表示节点，或者在本例中为神经元。
This we would call in CS50, the input.
在 CS50 中，我们将它称为输入。
This is what we would call the output.
我们将它称为输出。
But this is a very simplistic, a very simple neural network.
但这是一个非常简单的神经网络。
This might be more common, whereby the network, the AI
这可能更常见，也就是说，网络，人工智能
takes two inputs to a problem and tries to give you one solution.
接收问题的两个输入，并尝试提供一个解决方案。
Well, let's make this more real.
好吧，让我们更真实一些。
For instance, suppose that at the--
例如，假设在
suppose that just for the sake of discussion, here is like a grid
假设只是为了讨论起见，这里有一个网格
that you might see in math class, with a y-axis and an x-axis, vertically
你可能会在数学课上看到，纵轴是 y 轴，横轴是 x 轴。
and horizontally respectively.
分别代表水平和垂直方向。
Suppose there's a couple of blue and red dots in that world.
假设在这个世界里有一些蓝点和红点。
And suppose that our goal, computationally,
假设我们的目标是，在计算上
is to predict whether a dot is going to be blue or red, based
预测一个点是蓝色还是红色，根据
on its position within that coordinate system.
它在坐标系中的位置。
And maybe this represents some real world notion.
也许它代表着一些现实世界中的概念。
Maybe it's something like rain that we're trying to predict.
也许是我们试图预测的降雨量。
But we're doing it more simply with colors right now.
但现在我们用颜色来简化它。
So here's my y-axis, here's my x-axis, and effectively,
所以这是我的 y 轴，这是我的 x 轴，实际上，
my neural network you can think of conceptually as this.
你可以将我的神经网络概念化为这样。
It's some kind of implementation of software
它是一种软件实现
where there's two inputs to the problem.
它有两个输入。
Give me an x, give me a y value.
给我一个 x 值，给我一个 y 值。
And this neural network will output red or blue as its prediction.
这个神经网络会输出红色或蓝色作为它的预测。
Well, how does it know whether to predict red or blue,
好吧，它怎么知道要预测红色还是蓝色呢？
especially if no human has painstakingly written code
特别是如果没有人类苦心孤诣地写代码
to say when you see a dot here, conclude that it's red.
告诉它当看到一个点在这里，就断定它是红色的。
When you see a dot here, conclude that it's blue.
当看到一个点在这里，就断定它是蓝色的。
How can an AI just learn dynamically to solve problems?
人工智能如何动态地学习解决问题？
Well, what might be a reasonable heuristic here?
那么，这里可能有一个合理的启发式算法？
Honestly, this is probably a first approximation that's pretty good.
老实说，这可能是一个相当不错的初步近似。
If anything's to the left of that line, let the neural network
如果任何东西都在那条线的左侧，就让神经网络
conclude that it's going to be blue.
得出结论，它将是蓝色的。
And if it's to the right of the line, let
如果它在直线的右侧，就让
it conclude that it's going to be red.
它得出结论，它将是红色的。
Until such time as there's more training data,
直到有更多训练数据为止，
more real world data that gets us to rethink our assumptions.
更多真实世界的数据，让我们重新思考我们的假设。
So for instance, if there's a third dot there,
例如，如果那里有第三个点，
uh-oh, clearly a straight line is not sufficient.
哦，很明显，一条直线是不够的。
So maybe it's more of a diagonal line that splits the blue from the red world
所以也许它更像是一条斜线，将蓝色世界和红色世界分开
here.
在这里。
Meanwhile, here's even more dots.
同时，这里还有更多的点。
And it's actually getting harder now.
现在实际上变得更难了。
Like, this line is still pretty good.
比如，这条线仍然很好。
Most of the blue is up here.
大多数蓝色都在这里。
Most of the red is down here.
大多数红色都在这里。
And this is why, if we fast forward to today, you know, AI is often very good,
这就是为什么，如果我们快进到今天，你知道，人工智能通常非常棒，
but not perfect at solving problems.
但它并不完美地解决问题。
But what is it we're looking at here, and what is this neural network really
但是我们在这里看的是什么，这个神经网络到底
trying to figure out?
试图弄清楚什么？
Well, again, at the risk of taking some fun out of red and blue dots,
好吧，再次冒着让红点和蓝点失去乐趣的风险，
you can think of this neural network as indeed having these neurons, which
你可以把这个神经网络想象成确实拥有这些神经元，它们
represent inputs here and outputs here.
代表这里的输入和输出。
And then what's happening inside of the computer's memory,
然后计算机的内存里发生了什么，
is that it's trying to figure out what the weight of this arrow or edge
它试图弄清楚这条箭头或边的权重应该是多少。
should be.
应该是多少。
What the weight of this arrow or edge should be.
这条箭头或边的权重应该是多少。
And maybe there's another variable there,
可能还有一个变量在那里，
like plus or minus C that just tweaks the prediction.
比如加上或减去 C，只是调整了预测。
So x and y are literally going to be numbers in this scenario.
所以 x 和 y 在这种情况下实际上是数字。
And the output of this neural network ideally is just true or false.
这个神经网络的输出理想情况下应该是真或假。
Is it red or blue?
它是红色还是蓝色？
So it's sort of a binary state, as we discuss a lot in CS50.
所以它是一种二元状态，正如我们在 CS50 中经常讨论的那样。
So here too, to take the fun out of the pretty picture,
所以这里也是，为了让这幅漂亮的图画不再有趣，
it's really just like a high school math function.
它实际上就像一个高中数学函数。
What the neural network in this example is trying to figure out,
这个例子中神经网络试图弄清楚的是，
is what formula of the form ax plus by plus c
什么样的公式 ax+by+c
is going to be arbitrarily greater than 0?
将大于 0？
And if so, let's conclude that the dot is red
如果是这样，让我们得出结论，这个点是红色的
if you get back a positive result. If you don't, let's
如果你得到一个正的结果。如果不是，让我们
conclude that the dot is going to be blue instead.
得出结论，这个点将是蓝色的。
So really what you're trying to do, is figure out
所以你真正要做的是弄清楚
dynamically what numbers do we have to tweak,
动态地我们需要调整哪些数字，
these parameters inside of the neural network
这些神经网络内部的参数
that just give us the answer we want based on all of this data?
仅仅根据所有这些数据给我们我们想要的答案？
More generally though, this would be really representative of deep learning.
更一般地说，这将真正代表深度学习。
It's not as simple as input, input, output.
它不像输入、输入、输出那样简单。
There's actually a lot of these nodes, these neurons.
实际上有许多节点，这些神经元。
There's a lot of these edges.
有很多边。
There's a lot of numbers and math are going on that,
有很多数字和数学运算正在进行，
frankly, even the computer scientists using these neural networks
坦白地说，即使是使用这些神经网络的计算机科学家
don't necessarily know what they even mean or represent.
也不一定知道它们的含义或代表什么。
It just happens to be that when you crunch the numbers with all
只是碰巧的是，当你用所有这些参数来处理这些数字时，
of these parameters in place, you get the answer that you want,
你得到了你想要的答案，
at least most of the time.
至少大多数时候是这样的。
So that's essentially the intuition behind that.
所以这就是背后的基本直觉。
And you can apply it to very real world, if mundane applications.
你可以将它应用于非常现实的，即使是平凡的应用。
Given today's humidity, given today's pressure, yes or no,
假设今天的湿度，假设今天的压力，是还是否，
should there be rainfall?
应该会有降雨吗？
And maybe there is some mathematical function
也许存在一些数学函数
that based on years of training data, we can
基于多年的训练数据，我们可以
infer what that prediction should be.
推断出预测应该是什么。
Another one.
另一个。
Given this amount of advertising in this month,
假设本月的广告量是这么多，
what should our sales be for that year?
我们今年的销售额应该是什么？
Should they be up, or should they be down?
应该是上升还是下降？
Sorry, for that particular month.
抱歉，是针对那个特定的月份。
So real world problems map readily when you can break them down
所以现实世界中的问题很容易映射，当你能够将它们分解
into inputs and a binary output often, or some kind of output
成输入和二元输出，或者某种输出
where you want the thing to figure out based on past data what
你想让它根据过去的数据弄清楚是什么。
its prediction should be.
它的预测应该是。
So that brings us back to generative artificial intelligence, which
这让我们回到生成式人工智能，它
isn't just about solving problems, but really generating literally images,
不仅仅是解决问题，而是真正地生成图像，
texts, even videos, that again, increasingly resemble
文本，甚至视频，这些内容越来越像
what we humans might otherwise output ourselves.
我们人类可能自己输出的内容。
And within the world of generative artificial intelligence,
在生成式人工智能的世界里，
do we have, of course, these same images that we saw before,
我们当然有之前看到的相同图像，
the same text that we saw before, and more generally, things
之前看到的相同文本，更一般地说，还有一些东西
like ChatGPT, which are really examples of what we now call large language
比如 ChatGPT，这些都是我们现在称之为大型语言模型的例子
models.
模型。
These sort of massive neural networks that
这些大型的神经网络
have so many inputs and so many neurons implemented
拥有如此多的输入和神经元，
in software, that essentially represent all of the patterns
在软件中，这些神经元本质上代表了软件在被输入海量数据后所发现的所有模式。
that the software has discovered by being fed massive amounts of input.
这些模式是软件通过被输入海量数据而发现的。
Think of it as like the entire textual content of the internet.
把它想象成互联网上所有的文字内容。
Think of it as the entire content of courses like CS50
把它想象成像 CS50 这样的课程的所有内容
that may very well be out there on the internet.
这些内容很可能存在于互联网上。
And even though these AIs, these large language models
尽管这些 AI，这些大型语言模型
haven't been told how to behave, they're really
没有被告知如何行为，它们实际上
inferring from all of these examples, for better
从所有这些例子中推断，无论好坏，
or for worse, how to make predictions.
如何做出预测。
So here, for instance, from 2017, just a few years back,
例如，这里，从 2017 年开始，就在几年前，
is a seminal paper from Google that introduced what we now
谷歌发表了一篇开创性的论文，它介绍了我们现在所知的
know as a transformer architecture.
Transformer 架构。
And this introduced this idea of attention values, whereby
它引入了注意值的概念，即
they propose that given an English sentence, for instance, or really
他们提出，给定一个英文句子，或者实际上是
any human sentence, you try to assign numbers, not unlike our past exercises,
任何人类的句子，你试图为每个词分配数字，这与我们之前的练习类似，
to each of the words, each of the inputs that speaks to its relationship
为每个词，每个输入分配数字，这些数字体现了它们之间的关系
with other words.
与其他词之间的关系。
So if there's a high relationship between two words in a sentence,
因此，如果句子中两个词之间关系密切，
they would have high attention values.
它们将具有较高的注意值。
And if maybe it's a preposition or an article, like the or the like,
如果它是一个介词或冠词，比如 the 或 the 之类的，
maybe those attention values are lower.
它们的注意值可能会比较低。
And by encoding the world in that way, do
通过这种方式对世界进行编码，是否
we begin to detect patterns that allow us to predict things like words,
我们开始检测到允许我们预测像词这样的东西的模式，
that is, generate text.
也就是说，生成文本。
So for instance, up until a few years ago, completing this sentence
例如，直到几年前，完成这个句子
was actually pretty hard for a lot of AI.
对许多 AI 来说实际上是相当困难的。
So for instance here, Massachusetts is a state in the New England region
例如，这里，马萨诸塞州是美国东北部新英格兰地区的一个州。
of the Northeastern United States.
它位于美国东北部。
It borders on the Atlantic Ocean to the east.
它东部与大西洋接壤。
The state's capital is dot, dot, dot.
该州的首都是……
Now, you should think that this is relatively straightforward.
现在，你应该认为这相对简单。
It's like just handing you a softball type question.
就像给你一个简单的问答题一样。
But historically within the world of AI, this word, state,
但在 AI 的历史上，这个词，state，
was so relatively far away from the proper noun
距离它所指代的专有名词
that it's actually referring back to, that we just
相当遥远，以至于我们只是
didn't have computational models that took in that holistic picture,
没有计算模型能够捕捉到这种整体画面，
that frankly, we humans are much better at.
坦白地说，我们人类在这方面要擅长得多。
If you would ask this question a little more quickly,
如果你更快地问这个问题，
a little more immediately, you might have gotten a better response.
更直接一些，你可能会得到更好的回应。
But this is, daresay, why chatbots in the past been
但这就是，敢说，为什么过去聊天机器人
so bad in the form of customer service and the like,
在客户服务等方面表现如此糟糕，
because they're not really taking all of the context into
因为它们没有真正将所有上下文
account that we humans might be inclined to provide.
考虑在内，而我们人类可能倾向于提供这些信息。
What's going on underneath the hood?
引擎盖下到底发生了什么？
Without escalating things too quickly, what an artificial intelligence
不急于下结论，如今的人工智能，这些大型语言模型可能会
nowadays, these large language models might do,
做的事情是，
is break down the user's input, your input into ChatGPT
将用户的输入，你输入 ChatGPT 的内容
into the individual words.
分解成单个词。
We might then encode, we might then take into account the order of those words.
然后，我们可能会对这些词进行编码，考虑这些词的顺序。
Massachusetts is first, is is last.
马萨诸塞州排在第一位，is 排在最后一位。
We might further encode each of those words using a standard way.
我们还可以用标准的方法对每个词进行进一步编码。
And there's different algorithms for this,
为此，有不同的算法，
but you come up with what are called embeddings.
但你最终会得到所谓的嵌入。
That is to say, you can use one of those APIs
也就是说，你可以使用之前提到的 API 之一，
I talked about earlier, or even software running on your own computers,
或者是在你自己的电脑上运行的软件，
to come up with a mathematical representation
来获得词语的数学表示
of the word, Massachusetts.
比如词语，马萨诸塞州。
And Rongxin kindly did this for us last night.
Rongxin 昨晚好心地为我们做了这件事。
This is the 1,536 floating point values that OpenAI uses
这是 OpenAI 用来表示词语“马萨诸塞州”的 1536 个浮点数。
to represent the word, Massachusetts.
用来表示词语“马萨诸塞州”。
And this is to say, and you should not understand
也就是说，你也不应该理解
anything you are looking at on the screen, nor do I,
你在屏幕上看到的东西，我也不理解，
but this is now a mathematical representation
但这现在是输入的数学表示，
of the input that can be compared against
可以与其他输入的数学表示
the mathematical representations of other inputs
进行比较，
in order to find proximity semantically.
以便在语义上找到近似值。
Words that somehow have relationships or correlations with each other
词语之间存在某种关系或关联，
that helps the AI ultimately predict what
这最终帮助 AI 预测
should the next word out of its mouth be, so to speak.
下一个词应该是什么，可以这么说。
So in a case like, these values represent--
因此，在类似的情况下，这些值表示——
these lines represent all of those attention values.
这些线代表所有注意值。
And thicker lines means there's more attention given
较粗的线表示给定词之间的注意值更高。
from one word to another.
从一个词到另一个词。
Thinner lines mean the opposite.
较细的线表示相反。
And those inputs are ultimately fed into a large neural network,
这些输入最终被送入大型神经网络，
where you have inputs on the left, outputs on the right.
左侧是输入，右侧是输出。
And in this particular case, the hope is to get out
在这种特殊情况下，希望得到
a single word, which is the capital of Boston itself, whereby somehow,
一个词，即波士顿本身的首府，通过某种方式，
the neural network and the humans behind it at OpenAI, Microsoft, Google,
神经网络以及 OpenAI、微软、谷歌 背后的研究人员，
or elsewhere, have sort of crunched so many numbers by training
或者在其他地方，通过训练已经处理了大量数据
these models on so much data, that it figured out what all of those weights
这些模型在大量数据上训练，以至于它计算出所有权重
are, what the biases are, so as to influence mathematically
是什么，偏差是什么，以便从数学上影响
the output therefrom.
输出结果。
So that is all underneath the hood of what students now
所以，所有这些都在学生现在所感知的可爱橡皮鸭的幕后。
perceive as this adorable rubber duck.
所感知的可爱橡皮鸭的幕后。
But underneath it all is certainly a lot of domain knowledge.
但所有这些的背后，肯定有很多领域知识。
And CS50, by nature of being OpenCourseWare for the past many years,
而 CS50，由于过去几年一直是开放式课程，
CS50 is fortunate to actually be part of the model,
CS50 很幸运地成为了模型的一部分，
as might be any other content that's freely available online.
就像任何其他可以在网上免费获取的内容一样。
And so that certainly helps benefit the answers
因此，这无疑有助于提高问题的答案
when it comes to asking CS50 specific questions.
在提出 CS50 相关问题时。
That said, it's not perfect.
也就是说，它并不完美。
And you might have heard of what are currently
你可能听说过现在被称为
called hallucinations, where ChatGPT and similar tools just make stuff up.
幻觉的东西，ChatGPT 和类似的工具只是编造了一些东西。
And it sounds very confident.
而且听起来很有自信。
And you can sometimes call on it, whereby
你有时可以调用它，从而
you can say, no, that's not right.
你可以说，不，那是不对的。
And it will playfully apologize and say, oh, I'm sorry.
它会俏皮地道歉说，哦，对不起。
But it made up some statement, because it was probabilistically
但它编造了一些陈述，因为它在概率上
something that could be said, even if it's just not correct.
是可能被说出来的事情，即使它只是不正确。
Now, allow me to propose that this kind of problem
现在，请允许我提出，这种问题
is going to get less and less frequent.
会越来越少见。
And so as the models evolve and our techniques evolve,
因此，随着模型的演进和我们技术的进步，
this will be less of an issue.
这将不再是一个问题。
But I thought it would be fun to end on a note
但我认为用一个音符结尾会很有趣
that a former colleague shared just the other day, which
前几天一位前同事分享的，
was this old poem by Shel Silverstein, another something
是谢尔·西尔弗斯坦的这首老诗，可能是我们过去的童年
from our past childhood perhaps.
的一部分。
And this was from 1981, a poem called "Homework Machine," which is perhaps
这是 1981 年的作品，一首名为“作业机”的诗，或许
foretold where we are now in 2023.
预示了我们现在在 2023 年的位置。
"The homework machine, oh, the homework machine, most perfect contraption
“作业机，哦，作业机，最完美的机器
that's ever been seen.
有史以来最完美的机器。
Just put in your homework, then drop in a dime, snap on the switch,
只要把作业放进去，然后投入一角钱，按下开关，
and in ten seconds time, your homework comes out quick and clean as can be.
十秒钟后，你的作业就会出来，又快又干净，一尘不染。
Here it is, 9 plus 4, and the answer is 3.
这是 9 加 4，答案是 3。
3?
3？
Oh, me.
哦，我。
I guess it's not as perfect as I thought it would be."
我想它不像我想象的那么完美。”
So, quite foretelling, sure.
所以，相当预示了未来，没错。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Quite foretelling, indeed.
的确相当预示了未来。
Though, if for all this and more, the family members in the audience
不过，如果您想了解更多内容，现场的家庭成员
are welcome to take CS50 yourself online at cs50edx.org.
欢迎您在 cs50edx.org 上在线学习 CS50。
For all of today and so much more, allow me
为了今天以及更多内容，请允许我
to thank Brian, Rongxin, Sophie, Andrew, Patrick, Charlie, CS50's whole team.
感谢 Brian、Rongxin、Sophie、Andrew、Patrick、Charlie 以及 CS50 的全体团队。
If you are a family member here headed to lunch with CS50's team,
如果您是这里准备与 CS50 团队共进午餐的家庭成员，
please look for Cameron holding a rubber duck above her head.
请寻找 Cameron，她头上举着一只橡皮鸭。
Thank you so much for joining us today.
非常感谢您今天加入我们。
This was CS50.
这是 CS50。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]